Task number 23.
In this task we're going to use
divideAndConquer just like we did last week.
So, the definition of the
function itself is still the same.
The difference is that this time we're going
to make a function called “findSatisfying”,
and we're going to use
divideAndConquer in this function.
So, this function "findSatisfying"
should take a range and…
No. First of all, it should take
a condition like a predicate,
which is a function that takes
an integer and returns a Boolean (True or False),
and takes a range from
some number to some other number.
We're just going to call them a and b.
And then, it gives us “True” or “False”,
so, whether there is any number from a to b
that fulfills this condition,
so, if there is a number at least,
here in this range, that if you put it
into this function, it gives you True.
So, the first parameter that we're going
to give to divideAndConquer is this one,
which is a predicate that tests
whether an input is simple enough.
And it has this type signature. Now what
does “simple enough” mean in this case?
So, last week we had lists and we said
that when we have, for example, this list.
And this list here is not simple enough
because it consists of more than one element.
It has five.
So, we divide it
somehow and then we get such a list.
This one is still not simple enough.
This one is simple enough.
So, why is it simple enough?
Because we can test the only
element left in this list.
We can just test it. We
can deal with it directly.
And what about the empty list? Well…
The empty list is also simple enough
because it has no elements. It
doesn't need to be divided anymore.
So, what about this week?
This week, we have the
beginning and the end of the range. So, let's
say I want the numbers from one to five.
Then we get these numbers. Let's say
I want the numbers from one to two.
We get these.
Let's say I want from one to one.
We get just one.
And what if we
say I want numbers from three to
one? Then we get the empty list.
This means we have a function
here that takes a and b
and it gives us True only
when we have a equal to b,
which is this case, or when we
have a bigger than b which is
this case, for example. This means
we say a is bigger or equal to b.
So, the second parameter that we're going to give
to the function divideAndConquer is this one,
which is a function that computes
the output directly for simple cases.
And it has this type signature.
Now as we discussed here,
the simple cases... the only
case is that this function
considers simple,
are when a is equal to b, which means
that our range has exactly one number,
and when a is bigger than b,
which means our range is empty.
So, what do we do when we have one
element… I mean one number in our range?
It's easy. We just apply p to it and
see if it gives us True or False.
And now what do we do when
we have an empty range?
When we have the empty range,
our function should give us False
because if you think about it,
no matter what condition p is,
there are no numbers in this
range that can fulfill it.
So, yes it should give us False.
Let's write the function now.
The function takes a tuple a and b
(a,b). Actually, there is a mistake here.
This also should be a tuple
(a,b). And it gives you True only
when we have a equal to b,
which means we have exactly one
number in our range,
and at the same time
this number (let's take a or b, it
doesn't matter) fulfills the condition p.
Now the third parameter that we're going to give
to divideAndConquer is a function that splits a
non-simple input into two smaller
ones. And it has this type signature.
So, it takes a range from a to b,
and then it gives you two ranges…
two new ranges to… the two
halves of the original range.
So, the function…
Actually, I forgot to close this.
Okay… So, the function takes a and b
and returns two ranges,
the first of which starts with
a and ends with, let's say, m.
And the second one starts
with m+1 and ends with b.
And what is m?
m is (a+b)/2.
And now the last parameter that we're going
to give to the function divideAndConquer.
It is a function to combine the
outputs of two sub-computations,
and it has this type signature.
Now what does this mean?
It means that we already tested
two numbers, let's say x and y,
and we have the results of the test,
whether x and y fulfill the predicate p,
and we have True or False for x
and we have True or False for y,
and now we want to decide what we should
get. So, if one of these two numbers
at least leads to True, so,
one of these two numbers
at least fulfills the predicate
p, then we should get True.
Otherwise, if both of them are
False, then we should get False.
And what I just said is actually
the definition of the logical “or”.
And the logical “or” in Haskell
is just like any other function.
It is a function that takes two Boolean
values and gives us one Boolean value.
This means it already fits what we need
here. So, how about we just write it here?
And now, I think we are done.
Let's test it.
So, I'm going to open the file.
Main.
Yes. As you can see, it is working!